Department of Education Records UA071
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Department of Education Records
1954 -- 2014
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Department of Education
UA071
1.2 Linear Feet 1 box
31 Digital Object(s)
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Arrangement
This collection is organized in three series: Qualifying papers; Unprocessed accessions; and 2017 accessions.
Biographical / Historical
In the first years of the twentieth century, half-year courses in Pedagogy-later changed to Education-were taught by Professor Herbert E. Cushman of the Department of Philosophy, assisted by teachers from local secondary schools. The Chair of Psychology and Education was created for the academic year 1910-1911, and was filled by Colin A. Scott, formerly of the Boston Normal School and the author of Social Education. The catalog for that year states that "The work of the department is expected not only to prepare for teaching but to give a general idea of the facts of mental life, to study human and animal behavior in such a way as to be valuable to any student." Laboratory work would supplement reading, discussion and lectures. By the next year, however, Scott was gone, the heading was again simply Education, and psychology courses reverted back to the Department of Philosophy.
The next step forward for education studies came in the academic year of 1912-1913, when students were given the opportunity for observation and practice teaching in the schools of nearby Somerville. In the catalog for 1915-1916, the list of major departments included the combined entity Philosophy and Education. Students who desired to go into the teaching profession were advised to choose as their major the subject in which they intended to specialize. They should take the introductory Education classes, and pursue further Education courses for their graduate work.
As of 1924-1925, Education and Philosophy became separate departments. For the next few decades, the number of courses in the Department of Education steadily increased. To classes in the history and philosophy of education were added offerings in the social sciences, some of which concerned the measurement of learning outcomes. The Supervised Teaching component expanded to Arlington, Medford, Chelsea, Winchester and Melrose.
The 1939-1940 catalog stated that "the work of the Department includes a consideration of the pupil, the aims and desirable outcomes of the educational process itself, and the means and techniques for their most effectual achievement." The Department offered Master of Education and Master of Arts degrees. Students were alerted that different states have different certification requirements, so they should seek advice on how to tailor their course work accordingly. They were made aware of relevant courses taught in other departments, such as the teaching of English in the Department of English, history in the Department of History, modern languages in the Department of French, and physical education in the Department of Physical Education.
The academic year 1939-1940 saw the creation of the Division of University Extension (later called Division of Special Studies, then the College of Special Studies). The Division offered late afternoon, evening and weekend courses for the benefit of working schoolteachers. Classes were taught by members of the Tufts faculty. A Bachelor of Science in Education degree, offered to extension school students, was authorized in 1940.
Tufts entered into an affiliation with a number of teacher-training schools via the Division of University Extension. The student bodies of these affiliates were predominantly or solely made up of women.
The Bouv-Boston School of Physical Education, which became an affiliate 1942, offered courses of study in the teaching of physical education and in physical therapy. Bouv-Boston students could take liberal arts and basic science courses at Tufts. The school later moved to the Medford campus, but then ended its affiliation with Tufts in 1963 (whereupon it became associated with Northeastern University).
Tufts' affiliation with another institution proved more fruitful. The Nursery Training School of Boston, with which it affiliated in 1951, eventually grew into the Eliot-Pearson Department of Child Development. There had been an on-campus nursery school in 1940, which was suspended during the war years and did not reopen until 1949. It was dissolved upon Tufts' affiliation with the Nursery Training School of Boston, which had been founded in 1922 and was located on Marlborough St. in Boston. After its move to the Medford campus in 1954, the Nursery Training School (renamed in 1955 the Eliot-Pearson School for Nursery and Kindergarten Teaching) offered students of the Department of Education a chance to observe, as well as teach, young children. In 1964, the Eliot-Pearson School became the Eliot-Pearson Department of Child Study (later changed to Child Development).
The Department of Education grew during the postwar period, both in number of faculty members and courses offered to undergraduates and graduate students. Daniel Waite Marshall, then an assistant professor, became chairman in 1954, a position he would hold until 1971. An increasing area of focus was the training of prospective guidance counselors. In the academic year 1955-1956, a class in Citizenship Education was taught by members of the Tufts Civic Education Center. New course offerings in the 1960s included The Sociology of the School, Child Development (in association with the Judge Baker Guidance Center), and Education in Communist China (changed in the 1970s to Education in the People's Republic of China).
The department endeavored to welcome undergraduates who wanted to pursue a teaching career, graduate students working towards teacher certification, and working teachers who sought to further their education. To serve the latter population, an increasing number of courses were scheduled in the late afternoon, evenings, weekends, and summers. During the 1960s, the department started a Placement Office, through which a prospective teacher could learn about job opportunities in consultation with members of the nationwide network of Tufts alumni.
Degree requirements were further refined during this time. Undergraduates could follow a five-year program leading to a Master's degree. They were urged to decide early on whether to prepare for a career teaching in secondary or elementary school, since the respective accreditation requirements were different. The department had a recommended course selection list for each of those options. Student-teaching in local schools was emphasized as a crucial component of Tufts' teacher training. The graduate program offered Master of Arts and Master of Education degrees. The department identified several tracks which students could follow towards their degree. These included Preparation for Guidance, Teaching of Physically Handicapped Children (in cooperation with the Massachusetts Hospital School), Teaching the Emotionally Disturbed, Child Care Counselors, Health Professions, and, for a short time, Reading Specialist.
While a core group of courses persisted, there was some fluidity in offerings during the later decades of the century. Upon the establishment of the Eliot-Pearson Department of Child Study, some courses focusing on younger children migrated from the Department of Education to the newer department. Similarly, a cluster of courses centering on nutrition-offered in cooperation with the Department of Preventive Medicine together with the Frances Stern Food Clinic of the Boston Dispensary-moved out of the Department of Education during the 1980s and into the newly created Department of Nutrition. The department participated in the interdisciplinary Internship in Urban Social and Environmental Policy program in the late 1970s. Additions to the course offerings, such as Multicultural Concerns in Counseling and Psychotherapy, Learning Disabilities in the Classroom, and Teaching Through Drama and Improvisation continued to reflect contemporary issues and techniques.
In 1973, the department joined with the Department of Child Study to participate in a study-abroad program called Tufts in Education in England. Juniors and seniors were given the opportunity to attend the Alsager College of Teacher Education in Cheshire. The first enrollees took classes at Alsager in the spring semester of 1974. The program ended in 1978.
The academic year of 1991-1992 saw the launch of the H. Dudley Wright Program in Innovative Science Education, which offered fellowships for talented school science and mathematics teachers. According to the Wright Center's website in 2011, the institution is "dedicated to the creation and sharing of novel instructional techniques and interdisciplinary resources for pre-college teachers." The Wright program has been located in the Center for Science and Mathematics Teaching since its inception.
The late 1980s into the early 1990s was a period of flux as far as degree offerings were concerned. During this period, the Master of Education was discontinued. Thenceforth, candidates could pursue an M.A. or M.A.T. (Master of Arts in Teaching). In 1989, the undergraduate major in Education was discontinued (a minor in Education is still offered). Undergrads could choose a five-year B.A./M.A.T program. Starting in 1992, a C.A.G.S. (Certificate of Graduate Study) could be pursued in a specialized area, such as School Psychology. In the 1993-1994 academic year, the Department of Education and the School of the Museum of Fine Arts (which has been linked with Tufts for many years) collaborated to offer students who held a Bachelor of Fine Arts degree the chance to earn a certificate to teach art. This was followed by a Master of Arts program in Museum Education. The department similarly collaborated with the Department of Child Development to offer a certificate to teach elementary school children.
In the 2000s, a doctor of philosophy degree was offered in certain areas of specialization. There was a program to earn a Master of Science or a Ph.D. in Mathematics, Science, Technology and Education Engineering (MSTE Education), and one to earn an M.A. or Ph.D in German with Teaching Licensure (candidates were encouraged to take advantage of Tufts' study-abroad program in Tbingen, Germany). The decade also saw a number of M.A. degree programs created in association with specific institutions, such as the Shady Hill School in Cambridge, the Newton Teacher Training Institute in Newton, and the Advanced Math and Science Academy Charter School in Marlborough. In addition, an M.A. in Educational Studies was offered.
In the Department of Education's Faculty and Student Handbook of Programs and Degrees 2010-2011, ten different Master's degrees are listed, as well as the Ph.D. in MSTE Education (the Ph.D. in teaching German is no longer offered). The handbook lists as affiliated programs the Center for Science and Mathematics Teaching and the Center for Engineering Education Outreach.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains books, correspondence, qualifying papers of Department of Education students, reports, and a box of slides from an outdoor education camp. The construction of the Arthur M. Sackler Center for Health Communications is a significant topic in this collection.
Curriculum and Instruction -- Academic Departments and Programs; Curriculum and Instruction -- Student Work; Curriculum and Instruction -- Teaching Material
- Qualifying papers, 2007 -- 2014; UA071.001; 26 Digital Object(s)
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains selected papers submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for various degree programs in the Department of Education.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged alphabetically by author.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - From Functions as Process to Functions as Object: A Review of Reification and Encapsulation, 2007-02-01; UA071.001.001.00001; Burnett-Bradshaw, Camille S.
    A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Mathematics Education. Abstract: This qualifying paper explores the processes of reification (Sfard, 1987, 1989, 1991, 1992) and encapsulation (Dubinsky, 1991a, 1991b; Dubinsky & Harel, 1992a), as they apply to the concept of mathematical functions, and attempts to determine how both processes contribute to explaining the formation of the concept of function. The review of empirical studies on students' understanding of functions leads to the conclusion that neither reification nor encapsulation is without flaw; however, they have contributed significantly to partially explaining the formation of the function concept. This implies that more theoretical and empirical work needs to be conducted within this area in order for researchers and educators to have a complete explanation of the formation of the function concept.
    Functions; Concepts; Dept. of Education
  - Numerical Notation and the Place-Value Concept in Young Children, 2007-02-02; UA071.001.001.00002; Cayton, Gabrielle A.
    A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the Doctoral program in MSTE Education. Abstract: In recent decades, we have come to accept that children's appropriation of written numbers is not automatic or simple. Various studies of children's use of notation point to several different types of notational practice possibly linked to stages in the understanding of place value in base-ten (Alvara001, 2002; Brizuela, 2004; Scheuer et al, 2000; Seron & Fayol, 1994). Scheuer et al (2000) discuss two distinct types of incorrect numerical notation strategies used by children: logogramic and compacted notation. Logogramic notation refers to children who write the entire number literally, such as 100701 for one hundred seventy-one. Compacted notation refers to children who remove some of the zeros from the logogramic coding while still not condensing the number entirely into its conventional form, such as 1071 for one hundred seventy-one. Scheuer speculates that perhaps these two types of notational strategies stem from different conceptual ideas about the numbers themselves, yet the study does not explore these ideas, focusing only on written numbers. The study described in this paper examines Scheuer's arguments by comparing numerical notation strategies with children's performance on a task of decomposing numbers created by valued tokens that will provide insights into the children's ideas.
    Numerals, Writing of; Children; Dept. of Education
  - Developing Middle School Engineering Teachers: Toward Expertise in Engineering Subject Matter and Pedagogical Content Knowledge, 2007-02-01; UA071.001.001.00003; Hynes, Morgan M.
    A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the program in MSTE Education. Abstract: The purpose of this review is to examine various educational constructs and explore links to developing middle school engineering teachers. In our technical society today, learning and teaching engineering is becoming more and more important. National and state standards are beginning to include engineering content standards for K-12 classrooms. If teachers are going to begin teaching engineering they will, undoubtedly, need some preparation before they begin. In this review, I look at subject matter knowledge, pedagogical knowledge, and expertise and discuss how what has already been done in other fields such as math and science education can be used to inform future development of teaching engineering in the middle school classroom. Conclusions about how subject matter knowledge and pedagogical content knowledge impact teaching and learning along with insights from expertise literature are used to provide guidance for future research and potential professional development implications.
    Engineering - Study and teaching; Education, Elementary; Dept. of Education
  - Research Perspectives on the Teaching and Learning of Algebra, 2008-08-01; UA071.001.001.00004; Martinez, Mara V.
    A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Mathematics Education. Abstract: In this paper I will discuss different approaches to algebra adopted by researchers studying teaching and learning of algebra in the last thirty years (1977-2006). For each study reviewed in this paper, the goals are: to identify the central aspects of algebra (for example, algebra as the study of functions or algebra as the study of equation-solving), the mathematical problems researchers propose to use for teaching algebra and for evaluating learning, the used theoretical concepts, and main findings. In addition, I will provide a brief history of the evolution of the field of research on the teaching and learning of algebra, will discuss notions such as the role of equation solving techniques versus meaning making in the teaching and learning of algebra, the relation between arithmetic and algebra, algebra as a modeling tool, and the relation between algebra and proof.
    Algebra - Study and teaching; Dept. of Education; Tufts University
  - Middle-School Teachers' Use and Development of Engineering Subject Matter and Pedagogical Content Knowledge: A Pilot Study, 2008-04-01; UA071.001.001.00005; Hynes, Morgan M.
    A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in MSTE Education. Abstract: This paper reports on a study of two middle-school math and one middle-school science teacher as they taught an engineering unit. The study investigated the subject matter knowledge and pedagogical content knowledge these teachers used and developed as they taught an engineering unit that used LEGO to teach students the engineering design process through designing and building an assistive device that uses motors, sensors, and is computer controlled. Data collected from teacher interviews and classroom observations revealed the different subject matter and pedagogical content knowledge the teachers used to teach engineering that was new for them. The data revealed how a teacher's knowledge of physics or engineering can impact their teaching. The data also highlighted that the teachers rarely explicitly used their math or science knowledge to make connections to engineering. The study also illustrated examples of engineering pedagogical content knowledge the teachers developed while teaching the engineering unit. One central conclusion drawn from the study is that teachers would benefit from focused opportunities to develop the different specific types of engineering knowledge that they struggle with the most (i.e., physics concepts, mathematics principles, engineering design). The paper includes a literature review that provides a rationale and framework for studying the teaching of middle-school engineering, a description of the methods used, and results and implications of this study.
  - The Impact of Engineering Education at the Kindergarten to High School Levels: A Review of Research, 2008-07-01; UA071.001.001.00006; Ortiz, Araceli Martnez
    A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Engineering Education. Abstract: The aim of this review is to describe a selection of international research efforts in Kindergarten through Grade 12 (K-12) engineering education in order to define an organizing framework for the impact of engineering education on students' development of technological literacy, learning of math and science content, and motivation and understanding of science, technology, engineering, and math (STEM) careers. A considerable and renewed interest in the field of K-12 engineering education in the United States (US) motivates the need for sharing theoretically grounded research (Benenson, 2001; De Miranda, 2004; Householter, 2000; Norman and Roberts, 2001; Pellegrino, 1999; Zuga, 2000).
    Engineering - Study and teaching; Dept. of Education
  - Integrating Algebra and Proof in High School Students' Work with Algebraic Expressions Involving Variables When Proving, 2008-05-01; UA071.001.001.00007; Martinez, Mara V.
    A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Mathematics Education. Abstract: The overarching research question of the study described in this paper is: what are the consequences of an integrated approach to algebra and proof on students' mathematical knowledge while they work through a didactical sequence (i.e., the "Calendar Sequence")? In particular, the goal of this paper is to report on the challenges that students faced in their work with variables, and equivalent expressions while engaged in producing and proving conjectures, and how these challenges were overcome. Previous studies on algebra and proof (Barallobres, 2004; Bell, 1993) are scant nonetheless promising in regards to students' production of proofs using algebra in an integrated approach. I claim that the results presented in this paper provide promising evidence that an integrated approach towards algebra and proof, such as that implemented in the Calendar Sequence, has a positive impact on students' use of algebra as a tool to prove.
    Algebra - Study and teaching; Education, Secondary; Dept. of Education
  - Challenges and Promising Approaches in the Teaching and Learning of Introductory Physics at the Secondary Level, 2008; UA071.001.001.00008; Crowe, Jacalyn
    A qualifying paper submitted in partial fulfillment of the requirements for the degree of Doctor of Philosophy in Science Education. Abstract: The purpose of this review is to identify the challenges facing secondary teachers of physics, to explore the most common instructional methods currently in use and to propose future research that will lean heavily on the use of peer collaboration to foster strong conceptual change. Through this review, I will argue that: (1) Strong conceptual change or restructuring is needed for high school students to develop as Newtonian thinkers; ( 2) Peer-to-peer verbal interactions may have an important role to play in this process; (3) Combined quantitative and qualitative studies, at the secondary level, are needed to contribute to our understanding of this process for students enrolled in introductory physics courses; and (4) Careful analysis of interaction transcripts will be necessary to inform our understanding of the mechanism involved in conceptual restructuring in this setting.
    Physics; Education, Secondary; Dept. of Education
  - The Effect of Structured Peer-to-Peer Interactions on Conceptual Understanding of DC Resistive Circuits in Secondary Physics, 2008-06-01; UA071.001.001.00009; Crowe, Jacalyn